rbdigital.com 2018-10-07

# RECORDED BOOKS, RBDIGITAL PRIVACY POLICY

RECORDED BOOKS, RBDIGITAL PRIVACY POLICY
Effective August 1, 2018
C ONTENTS
RECORDED BOOKS, RBDIGITAL PRIVACY POLICY
     Contents
Privacy Statement for Recorded Books Inc.
What Information Does Recorded Books Inc. Collect?
     Information that you Give Us
     Automatic Information & Cookies:
     Log Files:
How Does Recorded Books Inc. Use the Information It Receives?
Does Recorded Books Inc. Share the Information It Receives?
     Agents:
     Partners:
Protection of Recorded Books Inc. and Others:
Will Recorded Books Inc. Sell My Personal Information To Other Companies?
How Secure Is Information About Me?
Links to Third Party Sites
Children
Breach Notification
Terms of Use, Notices, and Revisions
RBdigital Platform and Website Compliant with the Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA)
How to Contact Recorded Books, Inc.
Additional Information for European Union Users
     The EU General Data Protection Regulation (“GDPR”)
     What is ‘personal data’ under the GDPR?
     Who is the Controller of your Personal Information?
     Our EU Representative
     Your Rights
         About Our Forget Me Process:
     Our Legal Basis for processing your Personal Information.
     What Happens When You Do Not Provide Necessary Personal Information?
     Use For New Purposes
     Retention
     Personal Information from Third Party Sources
     Transfers of Personal Information to entities based outside Europe

PRIVACY STATEMENT FOR RECORDED BOOKS INC.
Your privacy is of great importance to Recorded Books Inc. ("We", “our” or “us”). As a user of this
website and/or one of our mobile applications (collectively, the "Site"), you are valued by
Recorded Books Inc. and We will take appropriate measures to protect the Personal Information
provided by, collected from or relating to you in connection with the functions, facilities,
products and services offered on the Site (“RBdigital Services”).
INDIVIDUALS LOCATED IN THE EUROPEAN UNION SHOULD BE SURE TO READ THE IMPORTANT
INFORMATION PROVIDED IN Additional Information for European Union Users IN THIS
DOCUMENT
WHAT INFORMATION DOES RECORDED BOOKS INC. COLLECT?
We gather information about you (your “Personal Information”) so that We can provide you with
the RBdigital Services, and improve and personalize your experience with RBdigital. Personal
Information that We collect falls into the following primary categories.
I NFORMATION THAT YOU G IVE U S
We receive and store the information that you enter at the Site or give to us in any other way off
line. For example, We collect the information that you provide when you create an account for
RBdigital – this means at minimum, your name, email address, and library card number. We may
also receive the same or similar Personal Information from your library to verify you are properly
eligible to use the RBdigital Services (as described below).
We also collect information you provide when you fill out the information in any “contact us”
form on the Site.
We collect the minimum data set that allows us to deliver the RBdigital Services you choose to
use and to assist you through Customer Support if you request it. If you engage our Customer
Support team they may collect your phone number and other information specific to resolving
your issue.
You can always choose not to provide some or all of the information We ask for, but this may
prevent you from receiving information or obtaining certain services that you desire.
Our service partners may collect additional information in the process of creating your account
on their sites. You control the information you give Recorded Books and our service partners.
A UTOMATIC I NFORMATION & C OOKIES :
Whenever you interact with the Site, We receive and store certain types of information. For
example, We use “Session Storage” or "cookies" to store information when your web browser
accesses the Site. We use Session Storage if permitted by your browser. Session Storage is
temporary browser storage. We use information stored there to enhance your browsing
experience at RBdigital.com. Session storage is deleted when you logout or in 30 days whichever

comes first. If session storage is not permitted by your browser, we use a cookie to store session
information. A cookie is an alphanumeric identifier, which We transfer to your computer via your
Web browser and store on your computer's hard drive. The cookie file allows us to recognize
your computer when you visit the Site. On most web browsers, you can control how cookies
work. You will find a "help" section on the browser toolbar. Please refer to this section for
information on how to receive notification when you are receiving a new cookie, and how to
turn cookies off. We recommend that you leave cookies turned on because they will enable you
to take advantage of some of the Site’s best features.
L OG F ILES :
This Site uses cookies to log IP addresses, browser types, track where a user came from, where a
user goes on our Site, most popular pages, least popular pages, and other similar types of
information for systems administration purposes.
The information gathered via these cookies does not directly identify any individual visitor.
However, it may render such visitors “indirectly identifiable”. This is because the information
collected is typically linked to a pseudonymous identifier associated with the device you use to
access our Site.
Log files associated with these and other Site processes are kept for no more than 60 days.
HOW DOES RECORDED BOOKS INC. USE THE INFORMATION IT
RECEIVES?
Recorded Books Inc. uses the information that users provide to the Site in a manner that is
consistent with the reason for which such information was provided. For instance, if a user
contacts Recorded Books Inc. with a question, Recorded Books Inc. will use the contact
information of that user in order to respond to that inquiry.
When you register online, We collect your name, email address, postal code, and library card
number if available to provide the services your library contracted for your use (as described in
the section entitled Information that you Give Us:. We only process this Personal Information to:
•   Establishing and maintaining your account on the Site;
•   Managing your use of the Site and its functionalities – e.g., administering content you’ve
    loaned (Checked Out) or are looking to loan (placed on Hold), or added to a Wishlist, sending
    you emails/notifications about content you might be interested in, etc.;
•   To pass your information to our Partners whose services you access via the Site;
•   To pass a small amount of information to business partners (Agents) whom we contract to
    provide services in support of the RBdigital website
•   To provide you with the customer support that We have agreed with your library that We
    will provide; and
•   Ensuring that you are properly entitled to use the Site – i.e., We cross-check your
    information against your library’s systems to ensure that you are a valid recipient of the
    services your library has purchased for its patrons.

•
DOES RECORDED BOOKS INC. SHARE THE INFORMATION IT
RECEIVES?
Recorded Books Inc. considers the information provided by our users to be a vital part of our
relationship with our users and We treat it with great care and respect. There are, however,
certain circumstances in which We may share such Personal Information with specific third
parties, as set forth below.
A GENTS :
Recorded Books Inc., like many companies that serve consumers, hires other companies to
perform certain functions. Examples include managing our database and mailing requested
information. When We employ another company to perform a function of this nature, We only
provide them with the information they need to complete the task and they are not allowed to
use that information for any other purpose. Our agent companies include:
       Agent          Service and Website
    Amazon Web cloud storage where the RBdigital website and databases are stored
          Services securely [https://aws.amazon.com/]
    Urban Airship to facilitate push messages to mobile devices
                      [https://www.urbanairship.com/]
           Google to assess website traffic in order to improve content, its presentation and
         Analytics delivery [https://www.google.com/analytics/#?modal_active=none]
          Firebase a Google product, tools for mobile application development
                      [https://firebase.google.com/]
       Crashlytics a Google product, real-time crash reporting, facilitates building and
                      running stabile mobile applications
                      [https://firebase.google.com/products/crashlytics/]
       MailChimp to manage mailing lists, and send email to our patrons and libraries
                      [https://mailchimp.com/]
P ARTNERS :
Recorded Books, Inc. partners with numerous companies to bring you the latest in quality
services. Depending on the services your library purchased, some, none, or all of these services
may be available to you. When you create a partner account to use a service, We share your
Personal Information with the Partner. We share only the information necessary to create and
maintain your account. However, the Partner may require additional information to setup your
account. We do not receive that information. It is kept by the Partner.

A complete list of our Partner Services and the information we share with Partners can be found
in the document RBdigital Service Partner Terms. We encourage you to view the document.
Business Transfers:
As We develop our business, We might sell or buy businesses, stores or assets. In transactions
such as these, customer information is generally one of the transferred business assets.
Moreover, in the unlikely event that Recorded Books or one of its business lines are acquired,
customer information may be one of the transferred assets. If such changes result in updates to
the Terms of Use and/or Privacy Policy, you will be notified when you login to RBdigital.com and
you will be given the opportunity to read and accept the new documents.
PROTECTION OF RECORDED BOOKS INC. AND OTHERS:
Except for the limited rights granted in Section II.1(a) of our Terms of Use, Recorded Books
and/or its licensors own and/or control all right, title and interest (including, without limitation,
all copyrights) in and to the Site, Site Content and Service. “Site Content” means any and all files,
text, graphics, hyperlinks, interlinks, search engines, images, software, illustrations, photos,
animation, video, audio, audiovisual works, designs or logos, information and other works of
authorship made available to you through the Site and/or Service. You agree and acknowledge
that you shall not acquire any ownership rights by accessing or using the Site, Site Content or
Service. You acknowledge and agree that modification of the Site Content or use of the Site
Content for any other purpose is a violation of Recorded Books’ and possibly other third parties’
copyright and proprietary rights.
WILL RECORDED BOOKS INC. SELL MY PERSONAL INFORMATION TO
OTHER COMPANIES?
Recorded Books Inc. will not sell your Personal Information to any third-party or otherwise
transfer it to any third-party for their marketing purposes.
HOW SECURE IS INFORMATION ABOUT ME?
We have put in place what We consider to be appropriate security measures to prevent your
Personal Information from being accidentally lost, used or accessed in an unauthorized way,
altered or disclosed. For example, your Personal Information is stored offline on a secure server
which is password protected.
We take steps to limit access to your Personal Information to those employees and other staff
who have a real business need to have such access. All such people are subject to a contractual
duty of confidentiality.

LINKS TO THIRD PARTY SITES
You may be able to access third party websites through links available on this Site You
understand and agree that your use of such third party sites will be governed by the privacy
policies of those sites and not by this Privacy Policy. Recorded Books Inc. shall not be responsible
for the actions of the operators of such third party websites. We have contracts in place whose
terms govern the relationship between Recorded Books, Inc. and the partners. These contracts
state that (as applicable) our partners will adhere to the standards of the GDPR.
CHILDREN
Recorded Books Inc. does not knowingly collect information from children under the age of 13.
We encourage parents and legal guardians to monitor their children’s Internet usage and to help
enforce our Privacy Policy by instructing their children to never provide information on this Site
without their permission. All of our EU patrons and some patrons outside the EU will be asked to
affirm that they are at least 16 years of age as they create or update their account with us.
BREACH NOTIFICATION
We have put in place procedures to deal with any actual or suspected breach or compromise
affecting Personal Information. In the event of any such breach, We have systems in place to
work with applicable regulators and our library partners to minimize the impact of any such
breach. In addition, in certain circumstances (e.g., where We are legally required to do so) We
may notify you of breaches affecting your Personal Information.
TERMS OF USE, NOTICES, AND REVISIONS
If you choose to visit the Site, your visit and any dispute over privacy is subject to this Privacy
Policy and our Terms of Use Agreement, including limitations on damages and application of the
law of the State of Delaware, United States of America. If you have a concern about privacy at our
Site, please send an email with a detailed description of your concern
to: rbdigital@recordedbooks.com and We will try to resolve it. PLEASE NOTE THAT THIS
PROVISION DOES NOT APPLY TO USERS BASED IN THE EUROPEAN UNION.
Our business and Site change constantly. The Terms of Use and this Privacy Policy may change
also. Our use of information that We receive and store is subject to the Privacy Policy and Terms
of Use in effect at the time of our use of such information. If We decided to change our Privacy
Policy, We will post the revised Privacy Policy on this Site. You will be notified to read and accept
the updated documents when you login to the website.

RBDIGITAL PLATFORM AND WEBSITE COMPLIANT WITH THE
AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT (ADA)
Recorded Books Inc. and RBdigital continually endeavor to make the RBdigital Platform and
Website accessible to individuals with disabilities in accordance with Section 508 of the
Rehabilitation Act. These pages also meet Recorded Books Inc.’ policy and guidelines for the
Section 508 requirements. If you have difficulty viewing any page via adaptive technology, please
contact us (rbdigital@recordedbooks.com) so that We can make the information available to
you.
HOW TO CONTACT RECORDED BOOKS, INC.
 Patron Support                       Copyright Complaints             Notices
 RBdigital Customer Service           Agent for Claims:
 877-77-AUDIO or                      Recorded Books Inc.              Recorded Books Inc.
 877-772-8346                         270 Skipjack Road Prince         270 Skipjack Road
                                      Frederick, MD 20678              Prince Frederick, MD
 Patron Support via email:            Attention: Neil Tress            20678
 yoursupport@recordedbooks.co                                          Attention: Neil Tress
 m                                    Facsimile: (410) 535-2761
                                      E-Mail:                          Facsimile: (410) 535-2761
                                      ntress@recordedbooks.co          E-Mail:
                                      m                                ntress@recordedbooks.co
                                                                       m
ADDITIONAL INFORMATION FOR EUROPEAN UNION USERS
T HE EU G ENERAL D ATA P ROTECTION R EGULATION (“GDPR”)
The GDPR is a data protection regulation of the European Union. It came into force May 25,
2018. The GDPR is relevant to Recorded Books, Inc. because We process the Personal
Information of individuals who are based in the European Economic Area (“Europe”) in the
context of making available the RBdigital Services to such persons.
This Privacy Policy is intended to meet our duties of transparency under the GDPR.
In particular, We want to make it clear to you what rights you have and how you can exercise
them. These are described in Your Rights in this document.
W HAT IS ‘ PERSONAL DATA ’ UNDER THE GDPR?
The GDPR definition of ‘personal data’ can be found here. Essentially, it means: information
about an individual, from which that individual is either directly identified or can be indirectly
identified.

It does not include anonymous information (i.e., information where the identity of individual has
been permanently removed). However, it does include ‘indirect identifiers’ or ‘pseudonymous
data’ (i.e., information which alone doesn’t identify an individual but, when combined with
certain additional and reasonably accessible information, could be attributed to a particular
individual). For example, certain of the technical information that We automatically collect when
you use the Site may constitute pseudonymous personal data by which you could indirectly be
identified.
To the extent it meets the definition in GDPR, each reference to how We deal with your
‘Personal Information’ or ‘personally identifiable information’ in this Privacy Policy should, for
users based in Europe, be read as a reference to personal data.
W HO IS THE C ONTROLLER OF YOUR P ERSONAL I NFORMATION ?
Recorded Books is a “Controller” of your Personal Information for purposes of the GDPR. In
addition, the library of which you are a member, will also have access to, and be a Controller of,
your Personal Information. This is because, depending on the context, we both determine the
purposes and means of how your Personal Information is used.
For our details, see How to Contact Recorded Books, Inc. above for contact details.
If you want to know how your library handles your Personal Information, you should check its
privacy policy.
O UR EU R EPRESENTATIVE
As noted above, We are not based in the European Union. For this reason, We have appointed a
representative based in the European Union, to whom you can address any issues or queries you
might have relating to our processing of your Personal Information and/or this Privacy Policy.
Our EU representative is: W.F. Howes, Ltd. To contact W.F. Howes, Ltd. Use the information
below.
Digital Customer Support: dataprotection@wfhowes.co.uk
W.F. Howes, LTD:
Unit 5, St. Georges House
Rearsby Bus. Park, Gaddesby Lane
Rearsby, Leicestershire, LE7 4YH
44 (0) 1664 423000
Y OUR R IGHTS
The GDPR gives you certain rights regarding your Personal Information. You may ask us to take
the following actions in relation to your Personal Information that we hold:
•    Opt-out. Stop sending you direct marketing communications. You may continue to receive
     service-related and other non-marketing emails.

•   Access. Provide you with information about our processing of your Personal Information and
    give you access to your Personal Information.
•   Correct. Update or correct inaccuracies in your Personal Information.
•   Delete. Delete your Personal Information.
•   Transfer. Transfer a machine-readable copy of your Personal Information to you or a third
    party of your choice.
•   Restrict. Restrict the processing of your Personal Information.
•   Object. Object to our reliance on our legitimate interests as the basis of our processing of
    your Personal Information that impacts your rights.
You can submit these requests by email to yoursupport@recordedbooks.com or our postal
address provided above. We may request specific information from you to help us confirm your
identity and process your request. Applicable law may require or permit us to decline your
request. If we decline your request, we will tell you why, subject to legal restrictions. If you
would like to submit a complaint about our use of your Personal Information or response to your
requests regarding your Personal Information, you may contact us as described above or submit
a complaint to the data protection regulator in your jurisdiction. You can find your data
protection regulator here.
In addition, if you desire to review your own Personal Information, visit your patron profile page
on the Site. From your profile page you can:
•   View and download the information we keep for you
•   Edit your personal information
•   Change the email address associated with your account
•   Request that we permanently forget your information.
A BOUT O UR F ORGET M E P ROCESS :
We honor your request to be “forgotten” immediately. We delete your information from our
systems and notify our Partners of your request as well. They will “forget” your information upon
receiving our request. We will send you a final confirmation email after which your personal
information will be gone from our client-facing systems and we will no longer be able to locate
your records or contact you. These steps take approximately one business day. The final traces of
your information in logs, backups, etc. will be overwritten through automated processes in less
than 60 days.]
Recorded Books Inc. reserves the right to maintain your Personal Information if Recorded Books
Inc. has suspended, limited, or terminated your access to our Site for violating the Recorded
Books Inc. Terms of Use, as necessary to comply with applicable law.
O UR L EGAL B ASIS FOR PROCESSING YOUR P ERSONAL I NFORMATION .
•   We only use your Personal Information as permitted by the GDPR. The GDPR requires us to
    ensure that we have a “legal basis” for each way in which we use your Personal Information.

    We are also required to inform you of each such legal basis for our processing of your
    Personal Information, these are described in the table below.
•   If you have questions about the legal basis of how we process your Personal Information,
    contact us.
•   Please note that where we rely on “legitimate interests” as the legal basis for our processing.
    We make sure we consider and balance any potential impact on you (both positive and
    negative) and your rights before we process your Personal Information for our legitimate
    interests. This means that, We have made an assessment that the nature and extent of our
    use of your Personal Information is necessary for our legitimate interests and your own
    interests and fundamental rights do not override those interests that We are pursuing.
  Purpose:            What this means:                           Legal basis:
  To provide the      This is the processing which is            Contractual Necessity
  RBdigital Services  necessary to perform the contract
                      governing our provision of the
                      RBdigital Services, including:
                      •   to establish and maintain your
                          account on the Site;
                      •   to manage your use of the Site and
                          its functionalities – e.g., administer
                          content you’ve loaned (Checked
                          Out) or are looking to loan (Hold),
                          sending you emails/notifications
                          about content you might be
                          interested in etc.;
                      •   to pass your information to our
                          Partners whose services you
                          access via the Site;
                      •   to provide you with the customer
                          support that We have agreed with
                          your library that We will provide;
                          and
                      •   to ensure that you are properly
                          entitled to use the Site and the
                          RBdigital Services – i.e., We cross-
                          check your information against
                          your library’s systems to ensure
                          that you are a valid recipient of the
                          services your library has purchased
                          for its patrons.

 Purpose:             What this means:                         Legal basis:
 Compliance, fraud We use your Personal Information as         Compliance with Law.
 prevention and       we believe necessary or appropriate      Legitimate Interests.
 safety               to:
                      •   Enforce the Terms of Use that
                          govern the use of the Site and the
                          RBdigital Services;
                      •   Protect our rights, privacy, safety
                          or property, and/or that of you or
                          others; and/or
                      •   Protect, investigate and deter
                          against fraudulent, harmful,
                          unauthorised, unethical or illegal
                          activity.
 Troubleshooting      To track issues that might be occurring Legitimate Interests.
 and Site             on our systems, audit the downloading
 improvement          of data from the Site and improve the
                      layout and/or content of the pages of
                      the Site and customise them for you.
 Analytics            To use data analytics to improve our     Legitimate Interests.
                      Site, offerings, marketing, customer
                      relationships and experiences.
 Anonymous data       We may also create, use and share        Legitimate Interests.
 creation             “Anonymous Data” (such as statistical
                      or demographic data) for any purpose.
                      Anonymous Data may be derived from
                      your Personal Information, but once in
                      aggregated form it will not constitute
                      ‘personal data’ for the purposes of the
                      GDPR as this data does not directly or
                      indirectly reveal your identity.
W HAT H APPENS W HEN Y OU D O N OT P ROVIDE N ECESSARY P ERSONAL I NFORMATION ?
Where you fail to provide Personal Information that we need to process based on Contractual
Necessity or for the purposes of Compliance with Law, we may not be able to perform the
contract we have or are trying to enter into with you (for example, we may not be able to open
your account, we may have to close your account etc.)

U SE F OR N EW P URPOSES
We may use your Personal Information for reasons not described in this Privacy Policy where
permitted by law and the reason is compatible with the purpose for which we collected it. If we
need to use your Personal Information for an unrelated purpose, we will notify you and explain
the applicable legal basis.
R ETENTION
We will only retain your Personal Information for as long as necessary to fulfil the purposes we
collected it for, including for the purposes of satisfying any legal, accounting, or reporting
requirements.
To determine the appropriate retention period for Personal Information, we consider the
amount, nature, and sensitivity of the Personal Information, the potential risk of harm from
unauthorized use or disclosure of your Personal Information, the purposes for which we process
your Personal Information and whether we can achieve those purposes through other means,
and the applicable legal requirements.
We also consider the inconvenience to you and your library should we delete your account due
to inactivity. Our policy for retaining the personal information used to maintain your Site account
is that accounts dormant for a three-year period will be closed and the user/patron forgotten.
Accounts showing activity will be maintained until otherwise requested by you or your library or
until you library ceases to engage Recorded Books, Inc. for services.
In some circumstances we may create Anonymous Data from your Personal Information (so that
it can no longer be associated with you) in which case we may use this Anonymous Data
indefinitely without further notice to you.
P ERSONAL I NFORMATION FROM T HIRD P ARTY S OURCES
In addition to the Personal Information that we collect directly from you, we may also collect
your Personal Information from third party sources. Please note that none of these third party
sources are generally available to the public.
As examples, we may receive your Personal Information from the library you are registered with,
as well as our Partners and Agents.
T RANSFERS OF P ERSONAL I NFORMATION TO ENTITIES BASED OUTSIDE E UROPE
We are a U.S.-based company. Although We do not have an establishment within Europe, as
noted above, the GDPR is relevant to us and our use of Personal Information of individuals
located in Europe. For this reason, We take appropriate steps to ensure that when We process
such Personal Information (despite the fact that We are not based in Europe) We do so in
accordance with the GDPR.

In addition, where We transfer Personal Information of individuals located in Europe to any of
the third parties outlined above, We take steps to ensure that We have implemented
appropriate safeguards to provide that such protection is maintained and is not undermined as a
result of that disclosure. This typically means that we endeavor to provide that all our partners
with whom we share your Personal Information (see here) are bound by contractual provisions
that establish appropriate safeguards for your Personal Information (including provision that
Your Rights are still effectively enforceable).
